Guide to the Clopton Family Papers, 1629-1915 (bulk 1775-1897)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Clopton Family papers 1629-1915 (bulk 1775-1897)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Clopton family.
77 Linear Feet 11,916 Items
Family correspondence and miscellaneous papers of four generations of the Clopton family and three generations of the Wallace family, centering in Virginia. The material ranges in date from 1629-1915 (bulk 1775-1897).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Clopton Family Papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library between 1938-1958.
Collection Overview
Family correspondence and miscellaneous papers of four generations of the Clopton family and three generations of the Wallace family, centering in Virginia. The earlier papers are genealogical records. Papers of John Clopton, Virginia legislator and U.S. Representative contain comments on politics in the Jeffersonian Republican Party, the Continental Congress, Jay's treaty, the Alien and Sedition acts, the Embargo act, and American relations with France. Letters to son, John Bacon Clopton, Virginia judge, relate to the operation of a plantation in New Kent County. Correspondence of Charles Montriou Wallace, Sr., a Richmond merchant, includes accounts of an overland journey to California (1849) and subsequent residence there, Reconstruction, and Virginia politics. Of interest also are Civil War letters from William Izard Clopton. Letters from a Richmond commission firm concern wartime and postwar business conditions. The collection also includes several memorandum books, scrapbooks, account books, legal casebooks, journals of trips to California, Texas and England, records of an unidentified temperance society, and financial records of a teacher.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Clopton family
Clopton, John, 1756-1816
Clopton, John Bacon, b. 1785
Clopton, William Izard
Wallace family
Wallace, Charles Montriou, 1825-1910
Merchants -- Virginia
Plantations -- Virginia -- New Kent County
Reconstruction (U.S. history, 1865-1877) -- Virginia
Temperance -- Societies, etc.--Virginia
California -- Description and travel
Richmond (Va.) -- Commerce
United States -- Politics and government -- 1789-1815
Virginia -- Economic conditions
Virginia -- Politics and goverment -- 1775-1865
United States -- Virginia -- New Kent County
United States -- Virginia -- Chesterfield County -- Manchester
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Genealogy (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1710-1808 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1809-1812 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1813-1827 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1828-1844 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1845-1853 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1854-1857 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1858-1861 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1862-1864 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1865-1867 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1868-1875 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1876-1886 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1887-1891 May (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, 1891 June-1897 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence, 1898-1906 (Box 15)
  - Correspondence, 1907-1911 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence, 1912-1915, undated (Box 17)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 18)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 19)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 20)
  - Legal Papers, 1629-1796 (Box 21)
  - Legal Papers, 1800-1869 (Box 22)
  - Legal Papers, 1870-1914, undated (Box 23)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 25)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 26)
  - Miscellaneous and Notes (Box 27)
  - Notes and Invitations, Cards (Box 28)
  - Invitations and Cards (Box 29)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1760-1860s (Box 30)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1860s-1880s (Box 31)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1890s (Box 32)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1900-1909 (Box 33)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1900-1920 (Box 34)
  - Bills and Receipts, undated and Miscellaneous (Box 35)
  - Pictures (Box 36)
  - Clippings, 1818-1890s (Box 37)
  - Clippings, 1900-1920 (Box 38)
  - Clippings: Confederacy (Box 39)
  - Clippings: Foreign and Poems (Box 40)
  - Clippings: Biographical, 1860-1910, undated (Box 41)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 42)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 43)
  - Clippings, undated, Printed material (Box 44)
  - Charles M. Wallace, Sr.: Literary Manuscripts (Box 45-52)
  - Charles M. Wallace, Sr.: Journal, vols. 1-4 [fragile] (Box 53)
  - Charles M. Wallace, Sr.: Journal, vol. 5 and other volumes (including estate expenses book, account books, list of voters for New Kent Co., Va., minutes of the Black Creek Temperance Society, and bank books) [some of these are fragile] (Box 54)
  - Miscellaneous volumes (including commonplace books, an account book, and an exercise book)[some of these are fragile] (Box 55)
  - Indentures, 1710-1794 (Box Sec. A OV4)
  - Joyce Wilkinson Clopton: Scrapbook, undated (Volume M:729)
  - Kate Clopton: Account Book, 1885 (Volume S:730)
  - [Kate Clopton?]: Housekeeping Account Book, 1862-1863 (Volume M:731)
  - Katherine [Kate] and [Maria] Adelaide Clopton: Tuition Book, 1863-1865 (Volume F:732)
  - Maria Adelaide Clopton: Housekeeping Account Book, 1857-1863 (Volume M:733)
  - Marie Adelaide Clopton: French Notebook, 1854 (Volume M:734)
  - ????? (Volume S:2360)
  - Charles Montriou Wallace, Sr.: Diary, 1865-1866 (accounts of travels in England, Scotland and deep South) (Volume M:2549)
  - Charles Montriou Wallace, Sr.: Diary, 1883 Nov.-1884 Oct. (This diary is written on back and over receipt book of William Wallace & Sons for 1870-1871, chiefly for shipments of whiskey.) (Volume M:2551)
  - Charles Montriou Wallace, Sr.: Diary, 1885-1886 (Volume F:2552)
  - [Charles Montriou Wallace, Sr.]: List of Books (Volume M:2555)
  - [Charles Montriou Wallace, Sr.]: List of Books (Volume M:2556)
  - Charles Montriou Wallace, Sr.: Notes on Local History, undated (Volume F:2557)
  - Charles Montriou Wallace, Sr.: Account of his early youth (Volume F:2558)
  - [Jefferson Wallace]: Account Book, 1857 (Volume S:2559)
  - Joyce Wilkinson Clopton Wallace: Notebook (knitting directions), 1898-1899 (Volume F:2561)
  - William Wallace & Sons: Daybook, 1860-1865 and Ledger, 1867 (Volume F:2562)
  - Adelaide Clopton: Record Book, 1861-1863 (Volume M:5284)
  - [John Bacon Clopton?]: Legal Casebook, 1820 (contains case forms, legal codes, court decisions, and other miscellaneous data) (Volume M:5285)